With every sun comes a new day. A new beginning.
每次日出都意味着新的一天 新的开始
A hope that things will be better today than they were yesterday.
希望今天会比昨天更好
But not for me. My name is Eep.
但对于我来说不是 我叫伊普
And this is my family, the Croods.
这是我的家人 我们是克鲁一家
If you weren't clued in already by the animal skins
如果你还没从我们的兽皮外衣和倾奇的前额
and sloping foreheads, we're cavemen.
发现我们是谁的话 告诉你 我们是洞穴人
Most days we spend in our cave, in the dark.
我们大多宅在洞穴里 宅在黑暗里
Night after night, day after day.
日复一日 夜复一夜地宅着
Yep, home sweet home.
对 温馨的家哪
When we did go out, we struggled to find food
一旦有机会出去 我们就想方设法
in a harsh and hostile world.
在充满危险的世界中寻找食物
And I struggled to survive my family.
我则绞尽脑汁独自逃生
We were the last ones around. There used to be neighbors.
我们是最后的洞穴人了 曾经有其他的洞穴人
The Gorts, smashed by a mammoth.
高姿一家 被猛犸象一脚踩成肉泥
The Horks, swallowed by a sand snake.
霍克一家 被沙蛇一口吞进肚里
The Erfs, mosquito bite.
尔福一家 被蚊子活活咬死
Throgs, common cold.
斯洛格一家 得个感冒就能死
And the Croods, that's us.
克鲁一家…就是我们啦
The Croods made it, because of my dad.
我们活下来全靠我那爹
He was strong, and he followed the rules.
他死壮死壮的 特别循规蹈矩
The ones painted on the cave walls.
就是我们洞穴墙上的规矩
Anything new is bad, curiosity is bad.
任何新事物都是不好的 好奇是不好的
Going out at night is bad.
晚上外出是不好的
Basically, anything fun is bad.
基本上任何有意思的事都是不好的
Welcome to my world.
欢迎来到我的苦逼世界
But this is a story about
但这故事要说的是
how all that changed in an instant.
那一切怎样在瞬间全改变了
Because what we didn't know was that our world...
因为我们不知道我们的世界
was about to come to an end.
马上就要玩完了
And there were no rules on our cave walls to prepare us for that.
墙上可没有规矩教我们如何应付这种情况
You are supposed to wait for my signal. Eep?
你应该等我信号再出来的 小伊
Boo.
嘿
Ow! No!
不要！
We've been in that cave forever.
我们都在那破山洞里呆一万年了
Three days is not forever.
三天可不是一万年
It is with this family.
对于这个家就是
Eep, would you come down here? You're being so dramatic.
小伊 给我下来呗？你太…招摇过市了
No, Sandy, come back here.
不 小沙 回来！
Remember the signal. Good girls wait for the signal. Ugga.
记住等信号 好姑娘都会等信号的 阿加！
As soon as I get Sandy, I'll go back in, and you can give the signal.
抓住小沙我就回去 你就可以发信号了
No, I mean, you're already out now.
不 但你们早出来了
I'm waiting for the signal, Dad.
我在等你信号的 爸爸！
Never mind, Thunk. Just come out.
没事了 桑克 出来吧
But if you don't give the signal, how do I know you're my dad?
但你要是不给我信号 我咋知道你是我爹？
The signal isn't so you know it's me.
信号不是让你知道是我
It's so you know I wasn't eaten by an animal.
而是让你知道我没被动物吃掉
Then why is the signal an animal noise?
那为什么信号是动物的声音呢？
Doesn't that just confuse things?
我是说这难道不会使人产生误会？
I don't know. I'm still waiting for the signal.
我还在等信号！
Mom, we're ready to leave.
妈妈 我们可以走了！
Mom?
妈妈？
Still alive.
还没死呢！
It's still early.
还太早了
And you're still fat.
你还这么肥
Breakfast formation!
排成早餐队形！
I want to see some real caveman action out there. We do this fast.
给我拿出点洞穴人的样子来！动作要快！
We do this loud. We do this as a family.
声音要响 团结一致
And never not be afraid!
学会害怕！
Yay, breakfast.
耶…早餐耶…
Who's up?
该谁了？
We'll flip for it. Call her in the air.
投姥姥决定 扔上去
Heads!
正面
Tails. Thunk is in. Positions.
反面 桑克上 就位！
Okay. Thunk...
好 桑克
Go.
去吧！
Come on, Thunk.
快去 桑克！
Way to go. Take it to the cave.
太棒了！把它带回洞里！
Release the baby!
放孩子咬它！
Get them, Sandy! Go!
去吧 小沙 去吧！
Get them, Mom!
抓住他们 妈妈！
Old lady down! Eep, avenge me!
老太太失手！小伊 替我报仇！
Thanks.
谢谢
Eep!
小伊！
Heads up!
接好！
Hey Dad, can we eat now?
爸爸 现在可以吃了吗？
Just wait till we get home.
回家再吃
Eep, put on the brakes.
小伊 过来踩煞车！
Eep!
小伊！
- Who is hungry? - All right! Good one, Dad.
- 谁想吃？  - 干得好 爸爸
Here you go, Thunk. Drink up.
给你 桑克 喝吧
- Sorry, Dad. - Looks like fast food tonight.
- 对不起 爸爸  - 看来得吃“快餐”了！
That's all right. I ate last week.
没事儿 我上周吃过了
Two knuckle warning!
两指节征兆！
Come on, Croods. Go, go.
快回去
Come on, come on. Darkness brings death. We know this.
快点 快点 黑暗会带来死亡！洞穴人都知道
The moon is full. Bath night.
月圆之夜 该洗澡喽
- Run for your life! - You too, Mom.
- 逃命去！  - 休想跑 妈妈
I don't want to lose my protective layer.
我不想丢掉保护层！
Mom, you've got ants.
妈妈 你都生蚂蚁了
See? Sandy doesn't fuss.
看 小沙都不跑
Is she still out there?
她还在外面？
You know she hates the cave, Grug.
你知道她讨厌呆在洞里 古勒格
Please come back tomorrow.
明天还要来哦
How could she not like the cave? It's so cozy.
她怎么能不爱洞穴呢？这么温馨
It is a little dark, Grug.
有点黑 不是吗？
It's not that dark.
没那么黑啦
Eep!
小伊！
Eep?
Come on, I have to close the cave.
快点 我要关门了
Eep!
小伊！
Okay, okay.
知道啦 来啦！
Come on.
快点
Eep! Come down!
小伊 下来！
- That was too close. - I was watching. I was fine.
- 太险了！  - 我看着呢 我没事
- What were you doing up there, Eep? - I don't know.
- 你去上面干什么 小伊？  - 不知道
- What were you looking for? - Nothing.
- 你去找什么？  - 没什么
- Then why did you go up there? - I don't know.
- 那你为什么上去？  - 不知道！
Why don't you know?
为什么不知道？
Stop looking for things.
别找东西了！
Fear keeps us alive, Eep. Never not be afraid.
恐惧让我们活下来 小伊 永远要懂得害怕
What is the point of all this?
这一切有什么意义？
What was that?
你说什么？
Why are we here? What are we doing this for?
我们为什么在这儿？我们这么做是为了什么？
No one said survival was fun.
没人说过求生是好玩的
Nothing is fun.
没有什么是好玩的
- Would you come down here? - Grug.
- 你能不能下来 小伊？  - 古勒格？
- Eep. - Grug.
- 小伊  - 古勒格
- Yes. - Off!
- 好  - 下来了
- Yes, I know. Okay, I'm trying to... - Off.
- 好 我试过了  - 走开！
I just don't see why she needs her own ledge, that's all.
我只是不懂她为什么需要独自呆着
- That's what this is about. - She's working through some things...
- 只是想问问  - 她在想事情
and she needs her own space.
需要自己的空间
What things? How long is this going to take?
什么事？要多久？
Really? She already doesn't listen to me. Hey!
真的吗？她都不听我说话了
See? She's listening.
看 她听着呢
If she wants to survive, she has to follow our rules.
要想幸存她就得遵守规矩
How about a story? Eep loves those.
讲故事怎么样？小伊喜欢听故事
That's a good ide... How about a story, huh?
好主意 想听故事吗？
Yeah, tell us a story.
好耶 快讲
Okay. Can I borrow that? Thank you.
好 借用一下 谢谢
Eep, your old favorite.
小伊！你以前的最爱！
I haven't played with that thing in years.
我都好几年不玩了
Tonight we'll hear the story of Krispy Bear.
今晚我们讲干脆熊的故事
A long time ago, this little bear was alive.
很久很久以前 这只小熊还活着
She was alive because she listened to her father...
她活着因为她听爸爸的话
and lived her life in routine and darkness and terror.
在黑暗与恐惧中一成不变地生活着
So she was happy.
所以她很快乐
But Krispy had one terrible problem.
但干脆熊有个致命的问题
She was filled with... curiosity.
她心中充满了…好奇
- Grug. - Yes. yes.
- 古勒格！  - 好 好
And one day, while she was in a tree...
有一天 当她在树上的时候
the curious little bear wanted to climb to the top.
这好奇的小熊想爬到树顶
And no sooner than she climbed to the top...
她刚爬到树顶
she saw something new and died!
就看见新奇的东西 然后就死了！
- Just like that? - Yes!
- 就那样死了？  - 对！
Her last moments of terror still frozen on her face.
她临死前的恐惧还凝结在脸上
Same ending as every day.
每天都一样的结局
I get it, Dad. I will never do anything new or different.
懂了 爸爸 我绝不会尝试新事物的
Good man, Thunk.
好孩子 桑克
All right, everyone sharpen your teeth, and let's pile up.
好了 大家磨磨牙 叠一块儿睡觉吧
Air.
憋死我了
You talk.
你会说话
I'm a person, like you.
我也是人 像你一样
Sort of like you.
和你…差不多吧
Okay, okay.
行了
Hey, hey, hey!
嘿 嘿 嘿
Would you mind not...
你能不能…
That tickles.
好痒啊
Hey, hey, hey!
嘿 嘿 嘿！
Quiet!
安静！
I'm not supposed to be out here.
我是偷偷跑出来的
Eep is gone.
小伊不见了
What? Grug!
什么？古勒格！
Stay in the cave.
呆在洞里别动！
Wow. You are really strong.
你真强壮
Hey! No! It's mine.
不！那是我的！
- Please! Wait. - No!
- 求你了！  - 不！
- It's dying! I can fix it! - No! I caught it!
- 快不行了 我能搞定  - 不！我发现的
Please! Please.
求你了
I hate the dark.
我讨厌黑暗
Come on, come on, come on.
来吧 来吧…
It does what you tell it?
它这么听话？
Yeah. Sort of.
嗯 算是吧
The sun?
是太阳？
No, no, no. Fire.
不 不 是火
Hi, fire.
你好啊 火
It's not alive.
它没有生命
But you said it was dying.
但你说它要不行了
Sorry.
对不起
It comes from where you come from?
你们来自同一个地方？
No. No, I make it.
不 我创造了它
- Make some for me. - Okay.
- 那给我也弄点  - 好
Make!
快点弄
It doesn't come out of me.
它不在我身上
Make! Make it!
快 快弄点！
You do this a lot.
你经常这么做吧
Are you dead?
你死了吗？
Can I have your fire if you're dead?
你要是死了我能拿你的火吗？
Hey, those are cold!
好凉的！
You think? Listening shells, activate.
你说呢？贝壳听筒 启动
I concur.
我想
Tiger girl, we need to leave immediately.
虎妞 我们得快点闪了
I don't even know you.
我还不认识你呢
I'm Guy.
我叫盖
Guy?
盖？
And this is Belt. Cook, conversationalist, navigator.
这是皮带猴 会做饭 会聊天 会导航
Also, keeps my pants up.
还能用来系裤子
What are "pants up"?
什么是“系裤子”？
Who are you?
你叫什么？
Eep.
小伊
Let me clarify, Eep. The world is ending.
告诉你 小伊 世界要毁灭了
What?
什么？
I'm calling it "The End."
我称之为“世界末日”
How do you know?
你怎么知道？
I have seen it. It's coming this way.
我看见了 正往这边来呢
First, the ground is going to shake. Then it breaks open. Everything falls in.
首先 大地会摇晃开裂 然后所有东西都掉进去
Fire. Lava.
火 岩浆
I don't mean to sound too dramatic, but...
我不想太夸张 但…
Believe me, everything we are standing on will be gone.
相信我 现在我们脚下的一切都将不复存在
We got to get to high ground. I know a mountain, that way.
我们得去高地 我知道有座山 在那边
It's our only chance.
这是我们唯一的机会
Come with me.
和我一起来吧
I can't.
不行
Okay.
好吧
Here.
给
If you survive, call me.
如果你活下来了 呼我
Thank you.
谢谢
Hello?
人呢？
Hey!
嘿
Dad!
爸爸！
Are you hurt? What took you?
你没事吧？什么把你抓来的？
Nothing. I left on my own.
什么都不是 我自己上来的
You what?
你什么？
Dad, let me explain.
爸爸 听我解释
You never let me talk.
你从来不让我说话
You're grounded.
我要关你禁闭
Hey!
嘿
Eep!
小伊！
Mom.
妈妈！
Grug! What happened?
古勒格！怎么回事？
You know what, I am so mad right now that I can't talk to her.
气死我了 我不想和她说话
Eep?
小伊？
You will never believe it. I found something new.
你不会相信的 我发现了新事物
New!
新事物？
New is a big problem!
新事物会造成大问题
Wait, wait!
等等 等等
Eep. Stay inside the family kill circle.
小伊 给我呆在绝杀圈里
- It wasn't bad. - "New" is always bad.
- 但它并没有不好啊  - 新东西总是不好的
No. He was nice.
不 他人很好
What? Excuse me? He?
什么？“他”？
I thought he was a warthog, but then he turned into a boy.
我一开始以为他是头野猪 但接着他变成了个男孩
Strange.
好奇怪
Usually it's the reverse.
通常是相反的情况
Eep's got a boy hog. Eep's got a boy...
小伊找了个猪男友！小伊找了个猪男友！
There was a boy.
是真的 好吗？
Watch. I'm going to call him.
我这就叫他
What is wrong with you?
你们都怎么了？
It was dangerous.
这很危险
It was beautiful!
这很漂亮
You want to see dangerous? Here!
知道什么是危险吗？看着
My sniffer!
我的鼻子！
Okay, that's it!
小伊 够了
We're going back to the cave...
我们回洞里去
and you're going to stay in there until you're older than...
你给我一直呆着直到…
her!
你比她还大！
What!
什么？
You can't keep me inside forever!
你休想一直把我关在洞里！
He said this would happen.
他说过会这样
Get to the cave!
快回洞里去
Go!
快！
Look out!
小心！
Stop!
停！
Is everyone okay?
大家都没事吧？
Yes.
没事
Grug, the cave...
古勒格 山洞…
it's gone.
没了
No.
不
You really need to see this.
快看
We should go there!
我们得去那儿！
No. No one is going anywhere.
不 不 哪儿都不许去
What else did that boy say?
那小子还说了什么？
Grug?
古勒格？
Just go! Just go!
快走！
Go!
快！
One, two, three, four, five...
一 二 三 四 五…
Six.
六
Where are we?
我们在哪儿？
I don't know. I'm not sure.
我不知道
Down.
在下面
In a lower place.
一个更低的地方
But one thing is for sure, we can't go back the way we came.
不过可以确定我们无法原路返回了
Sandy? What is it?
小沙？是什么？
No, no, no. Wait. Come back, Sandy!
不 不 等等 回来 小沙
We can't be out in the open like this.
我们不能这么在外面呆着
We need a cave.
我们需要找个山洞
Now, step where I step.
踩着我的脚印走
Okay. Stay quiet.
好了 不要出声
Hopefully, nothing big knows we're here yet.
希望不要被大动物察觉
Wait.
等等！
Okay.
好了
Wait.
等等！
Okay.
好了
Wait!
等等！
Wait.
Okay.
好了
Wait.
等等！
等等
So, Dad...
爸爸
just to be clear, are we looking for the exact same cave?
只想确定一下 我们要找一模一样的山洞吗？
If it was me... I'm just throwing this out there...
如果是我…我是说如果
if it was me choosing the cave...
让我选山洞
I would go with a smaller cave.
我会选个小点儿的
Wait.
等等！
Dad?
爸爸！
I'll take care of this.
我来搞定
All right, Dad, get them! Go get them!
来吧 爸爸 揍它们
Now you got them right...
你把它们…
Man, they're really...
它们真…
I'm loving this.
太爽了！
Dad, I got it.
爸爸 我懂了
Just stop running into their fists.
别老往它们拳头上撞！
Grug, when you're done, we should get going.
古勒格 你爽够了我们就上路吧
That's right. You can't get past this!
对了！知道敌不过这个吧！
Climb! Climb! Climb!
爬！爬！快爬！
Cave!
有山洞！
Go! Go!
快！快！
Come on! Hurry up. Let's go.
快走 快点！走！赶紧！
Look! This cave has a tongue. Awesome!
快看！这山洞有舌头耶！太酷了！
Okay.
好了
That's one, two, three, four, five, six.
一 二 三 四 五 六…
And seven...
七
if we're counting Chunky the Death Cat.
如果算上这只死肥猫的话
It's scared of the dark.
它怕黑！
Wait, we're scared of the dark.
等等 我们也怕黑！
Kill circle!
绝杀阵型！
Eep!
小伊！
- Cavies! - "Cavies"?
- 是洞人！  - 洞人？
Cavemen! Stand back! They're practically animals.
就是穴居人！退后！他们和野兽没什么分别
- You see their bony, sloping foreheads? - Yeah.
- 看见他们多骨 倾斜的前额了？  - 嗯！
The huge primitive teeth?
原始的大獠牙？
Yeah.
嗯
The excessive body hair.
过多的体毛？
That one has got a tail.
这个还有尾巴！
Yeah.
嗯
All right. Close your eyes. I'm going to have to take their lives.
好了 闭上眼睛 我要杀了他们
No! It won't help. They're my family.
不 不行 他们是我家人
What?
什么？
The sun is in his hands!
太阳在他手中！
No, no. It's "fire."
不 不 是火！
Where did it come from?
哪儿来的？
He made it.
他造的
Make some for me!
给我整点！
It doesn't come out of him.
他身上不产这个
Make. Make it!
整啊！整点儿！
You're a lot like your daughter.
你可真像你女儿
Great, now he's broken.
好了 现在他被你整坏了！
It's a baby sun.
是小太阳！
Hey, stay back. We don't know what it wants.
退后！我们不知道它想要什么
Now, we'll all sit here and wait for the sun to come back.
现在我们坐在这儿等太阳回来
And tomorrow we'll find a new cave...
明天我们找个新山洞
and pretend today never happened.
假装今天什么都没发生过
Isn't this fun, Eep?
这有意思吧 小伊？
Eep, don't touch him.
小伊 别碰他！
Goodness knows where he's been.
谁知道他去过哪儿
Dad, Sandy is hurting fire.
爸爸 小沙在弄火！
Sandy, no. Fire is not a plaything.
小沙！不！火不是用来玩的
What a cute little guy.
多可爱的小伙子啊
Hey. Stay back.
退后！
No, no, no, wait!
不 不 不 等等！
It likes me.
它喜欢我！
Hey! It's biting me!
它在咬我！
Thunk! Try hiding from it in the tall, dry grass!
桑克！快去干草丛里躲躲！
No, stop. Please, I'm only nine.
别这样 求你了！我才九岁！
They're biting me!
它还在咬我！
More fire babies.
火宝宝！
So, your dad, he is trying to kill me.
你爸爸刚才想杀了我
Yeah. But I won't let him.
对 但我不会让他得逞的
Hold on, son. Come back!
挺住 儿子 回来！
No, stop! Let me go!
它停不了 别碰我！
Get out! Out! Out!
滚开！
Eat up, babies!
尽情地吃吧 宝宝们！
No, stop touching me!
别碰我！
Die!
要死了！
I win!
我赢了！
They're not so scary once you get to know them.
一旦了解了他们就不觉得可怕了
Who are you people?
你们到底是谁？
I'm sorry.
忘介绍了
We're the Croods!
我们是克鲁家族！
And you are?
你是？
Guy.
我叫盖
Hi, Guy.
嗨  盖
Wow!
哇
It looks like magic.
看起来像变戏法！
And smells like food.
闻起来很好吃耶
No, don't eat it, it's new.
别吃 是新事物
Still alive!
还活着！
Come on, keep eating.
来吧 继续吃！
Hey, where is Guy?
盖呢？
No!
不！
Going somewhere?
要去哪儿啊？
The mountain? High ground? End of the world, remember?
上山 上高地 世界末日 记得吗？
That already happened. It destroyed our cave.
早发生了 毁了我们的山洞
No. That was just the beginning of the end.
不 那只是末日的开始
The end of the end is still coming.
结尾还没来呢
Eep. Drop it.
小伊 放下他
We can't let him go!
我们不能让他走！
What if we don't find a cave before sunset?
万一日落前我们没找到山洞怎么办？
What if it takes a few days?
万一要找好几天怎么办？
What if the birds come back?
万一那些鸟回来了怎么办？
We need his fire, dummy!
我们需要他的火 呆瓜！
Fine. You're staying with us until we find a cave.
好吧 在找到山洞前你和我们呆在一起
What? No, I'm not. Don't make me a part of this!
什么？不 不行！放了我吧
Stay here if you want, but let me go.
你们愿意就留下 放了我
I've got a dream...
我有理想
a mission, a reason to live!
有使命 有活着的理由！
Not anymore.
现在没了！
I've got an idea.
有了
Let's go to that mountain.
我们去那座山吧
It's too far.
太远
Dad really has his heart set on a cave.
爸爸只想着山洞
There are caves on that mountain.
那山上有山洞
Have you been there?
你去过？
It's a mountain.
山嘛
Mountains are safe. Mountains have caves.
很安全 有山洞
And water. And sticks.
水 手杖
Mom? Did you hear that? I can get my own stick!
妈妈 你听见了吗？我能有自己的手杖了！
Yes. Sticks and caves. Caves and sticks.
没错 手杖 还有山洞 山洞 手杖
Crazy sticks. Let's go.
神奇的手杖 走吧
Quiet!
别出声！
That thing is weird.
那东西好奇怪
No, no, no. It's okay, Sandy.
别 别 别 没事 小沙
That's just Belt.
那只是皮带猴
I've made a decision.
我决定了
We're going to that mountain.
我们去那座山！
Don't ask me why. Just a hunch.
别问我为什么 只是直觉
Just feels right.
感觉那是对的
I don't know, Grug. We've never really walked that far.
我不清楚 古勒格 我们从未走过那么远的路
I don't think my feet can do that.
我怕我的脚受不了
I'll never live long enough to get there.
我怕我没法活着走到那
Let's do it.
那就上路吧
Come on, just think.
来吧 想想
Our whole family packed together on a long, slow, trip across country?
一家人其乐融融地享受一段漫长缓慢的旅行
Days and nights with just each other.
朝夕相处 亲密无间
We'll tell stories. We'll laugh.
充满了故事和欢笑
We'll become closer as a family.
我们会更爱彼此
Get her off!
让她下去！
If you're not ready to challenge her, then don't look her in the eye.
如果你没准备好和她打 就不要看她的眼睛
Could you keep your big giant arms on your side of the trail?
你能看好自己的大胳膊吗？别老撞我！
Isn't this fun? We're taking our first trip together.
这有趣吧？我们第一次一起旅行
Stop shoving, or I will pull out your tongue!
别推我 否则揪掉你舌头！
Do you want me to turn this family around? Do you?
你想让我们掉头回去？想吗？
Because I will turn this family around so fast!
我立即就可以让大家打道回府！
Dad, I gotta go!
爸爸 我要嘘嘘！
- Come on, you can hold it. - I don't think so.
- 得了 你能憋住的  - 憋不住
Sandy, take that out of your mouth.
小沙 把它吐出来
I'm touching...
我在摸…
Dad, I still gotta go!
爸爸 我还是想尿！
Fine. Just go behind one of those lumpy things and make it fast.
好吧 别闹了 那你快点
- Something bit me! - I don't blame it.
- 有东西咬我  - 活该！
Dad, can I take a turn carrying him?
爸爸 我能扛他吗？
No.
不行
- How about now? - No.
- 现在呢？  - 不行！
- Now? - No.
Now?
现在呢？
I can do this all day long.
我可以扛一整天
No, no, no and still no.
不行 还是不行！
I'm not dying on an empty stomach.
我可不想当饿死鬼
Grug, we're all pretty tired!
古勒格 我们都要累死了
We'll eat when we get there.
等到那就吃饭
It's taking too long!
等不及了！
I'm grabbing a snack.
我先吃点点心
Don't do that. He will cut you.
别！他会刺你的
That's not food, he's a pet. My pet.
他不是食物 是宠物 我的宠物
What's a pet?
什么是宠物？
An animal you don't eat.
你不能吃的动物
We call those "children."
我们只是不吃小孩儿
No man should have a pet. It's weird and wrong.
养什么宠物 让人搞不懂
- It's food! - No, please!
- 那是…食物！  - 不 求你了！
Not that. That!
不是他 是那里！
Food fixes everything.
有食物就能解决一切
Show me your hunting face.
进入狩猎状态
Not you. You're still grounded.
不是你！你还在关禁闭
Come on, Thunk.
来吧 桑克
My feet hurt.
我脚疼
- You look tense. - I'm not tense.
- 你挺紧张啊  - 我不紧张
Angry girl wants to be doing what they're doing.
气呼呼的女孩想参与狩猎
I wasn't ready.
我还没准备好
Hang on, Thunk, I'm coming!
坚持住 桑克 我来了
Why are you doing this?
为什么老追我？
What are they doing?
他们在干什么？
Hunting.
狩猎
Get it off! You stay away from me.
离我远点！
No, seriously, what are they doing?
别蒙我了 他们到底在干吗？
You've got a ton of eggs. Just make another egg.
你那么多蛋呢 再下一个不就得了！
Now you're just rubbing it in.
你还觉得我不够惨是不？
There, who's hungry for scorpion?
来吧 谁想吃蝎子？
What happened to the egg and the bird?
鸟和蛋呢？
We lost him.
没逮到
But when the bird stepped on me and pushed me into the ground...
但是当鸟落在我身上把我轧进地里时
the scorpion grabbed a hold of me...
这蝎子过来占便宜
and one thing led to another and here we are eating him.
一事生一事 结果它反倒成了我们的盘中餐
So, win-win.
双赢啊
Not enough. Not enough! I need more.
不够吃 不够吃 我还要！
I need more.
我还要！
Look at that. She's not going to eat me, right?
快看 她不会吃我吧？
You're too skinny.
你太瘦了
If she was going to eat anyone it would be...
如果她想吃人 她会选…
Mom!
妈妈！
She's locked her jaw!
她不松嘴！
Get a stick! Get a stick!
用手杖
Stay away!
滚开！
You sick old monster!
你这个变态的老禽兽！
Hurry! Put the stick in her mouth!
快！用手杖撬开她的嘴！
Hold her still. Use a rock.
稳住她 用石头砸
Ugga, would you just hit her legs?
快砸她的腿啊！
Why are you rolling away?
为什么滚走哪？
I just want something to eat.
我就想找点吃的去！
You have bug for dinner. Plenty of bug!
你就吃虫子吧 管够！
Please.
求你了！
I'll let you help me hunt.
我让你帮我狩猎
Really?
真的？
Don't wait on me. They're all over me.
别管我了！
Tell my story.
把我的传说流传下去
Okay.
好了
What do you call this?
你管这个叫什么？
A trap.
陷阱
What does it do?
会怎样？
Well...
呃
How long have you been alone?
你这么寂寞有多久了？
So, what do we do?
接下来我们干什么？
How's your acting?
你的演技怎么样？
You're good at this.
不错啊
No. Sorry.
对不起
Okay.
没事
- Yeah, that's yours. - Excuse me.
- 那是你的  - 抱歉
Your other hand...
另一只手
- That's my arm. - Okay, I'm moving it.
- 那是我的手！  - 好 我拿开…
It didn't step in your trapything.
它没踩到你的陷阱
Yeah, I noticed!
对 我发现了
Where's Eep?
小伊呢？
She's awesome.
太牛了
Eep!
小伊！
Dad, no!
爸爸 不！
It's an avalanche of flavor.
味道真是棒极了！
Looks like we won't be having any leftovers.
看来没有剩菜了
What are "left overs"?
剩菜是什么？
When you have so much food to eat, you have some left over.
当食物过多的时候会剩下些的
We never have that much food.
我们从来都没那么多食物的
Grug, how about a story?
古勒格 讲个故事吧？
That's a good idea. How about a story?
好主意 讲个故事怎么样？
Yeah, tell us a story!
耶 好耶！快讲啊！
Once upon a time, there was a little tiger...
从前有个小老虎
who lived in a cave with her family.
和家人住在山洞里
There were a lot of rules...
规矩有很多
but the big, simple one was to never leave the cave at night.
但最简单最重要的一条是 绝不要在晚上离开山洞
And the door was so heavy, you'd think it would be easy to remember.
洞门很重 应该很容易记住的
So easy to remember!
是啊 多容易啊
I know.
我知道
But, while everyone was asleep...
但当大家都睡着的时候
she went out anyway.
她还是跑了出去
- No! - Yes!
- 不！  - 没错！
And no sooner than she did, their cave was destroyed...
结果山洞马上就毁了
and everyone had to go on this long, sucky walk...
大家不得不踏上一个漫长无聊的旅程
with some weirdo they met...
还遇到了一个怪小子
and die!
最后全死了！
The end.
讲完了
I did not see that coming. Twist ending.
这个揪心的结局好突然啊
My stories never end like that.
我的故事可不会这样
Yes! Two stories in one night!
太棒了！今晚可以听两个故事！
Okay. But it won't be as good as Grug's.
好吧 但我没古勒格讲得好
Once upon a time, there was a beautiful tiger.
从前 有一只美丽的小老虎
She lived in a cave with the rest of her family.
她和家人住在山洞里
Her father and mother told her, "You may go anywhere you want...
她的父母告诉她去哪儿都行
"but never go near the cliff, for you could fall."
但千万别去悬崖 你会掉下去的
And die. Good story.
然后就死了 不错的故事
But when no one was looking...
但当没人的时候
she'd go near the cliff...
她就会去悬崖
for the closer she came to the edge...
因为她越靠近悬崖边
the more she could hear, the more she could see...
她就会听到越多 看到越多
the more she could feel.
感受到越多的东西
Finally...
最后
she stood at the very edge.
她站在了悬崖边上
She saw a light.
她看见了亮光
She leaned out to touch it...
她伸手去摸
and she slipped.
她滑倒了
And she fell.
她掉下去了
And she flew.
她飞起来了
Where did she fly?
她飞向哪儿了？
Tomorrow.
明天
Tomorrow?
明天？
A place with more suns in the sky than you can count.
一个天空中挂满了太阳的地方
It would be so bright.
那得老亮了
A place not like today, or yesterday.
一个与今天和昨天都不同的地方
A place where things are better.
一个更加美好的地方
Tomorrow isn't a place.
明天不是个地方
You can't see it!
你看不见的
Yes, it is.
可以的
I've seen it.
我见过
That's where I'm going.
那就是我要去的地方
We are going to shut our eyes and sleep.
好了 我们该闭眼睛睡觉了
And when we wake up...
睡醒后
we're going to find the place that has everything we want.
我们就去寻找那片传说中的乐土
Tomorrow?
是明天？
A cave.
是山洞
That was too close. It almost caught us.
太险了 差点就玩完了
I was watching. We were fine.
我看着呢 没事呢
We gotta move faster.
我们得走快点儿
Do you people have any other speed aside from "wander"?
你们除了闲逛模式还有别的速度吗？
I'll take a shamble at this point.
要是我这时就会快起来
Hey, do you have a minute?
嘿 你有空吗？
How did the tiger fly?
老虎怎么飞起来的？
I only share when I'm outside the log.
在树桩里我不想讲
I'm funny that way.
出来讲才好玩
Leave this to me.
这交给我吧
Hey, Thunk...
桑克
you have a spider on your face.
你脸上有蜘蛛
He's loose!
他跑了！
Do not step on those weird pointy rocks.
别踩这些奇怪的尖石头！
Do you mean these rocks?
你是说这些？
Do not step on these rocks!
怎么能不踩这些石头？
Step aside, girls.
站到边上去 丫头
Hello? Nobody's listening! No one is listening.
嘿 没人在听！没人在听！
You cannot walk on those!
你们不能踩！
Get back here now!
回来！回来！
There goes our chance for survival.
我们逃生的希望跑了
And our log!
还有我们的树桩！
Okay.
好吧！
Jumping doesn't help. It does briefly...
跳起来也没用 起来时不疼
but it doesn't get better.
落下来就疼了！
Don't walk on your hands. The hands do not help at all.
不要用手 也不起作用！
Come on.
走吧
I can help you...
我可以帮你们
but we're going to have to make a few changes around here.
但规矩得改改
The log ride is over.
树桩之旅结束了
Drop the log.
扔掉树桩
Now, kick it away.
踢一边去
Farther.
远点
Really?
真远哪
Okay, smart "Guy"...
好了 聪明的盖
now what?
现在呢？
Good fish, good fish.
好鱼鱼 好鱼鱼
Okay. Now you can look.
好了 你可以睁开眼睛了
I love them! Where are my feet?
好喜欢！但我的脚呢？
They're still there!
还在呢
Okay.
好吧
You're really heavy.
你真沉啊
Really?
是吗？
Thank you!
谢谢
Hey. Wait!
等等！
Okay.
好
She's up. We're good. I'm good.
她起来了 没事了 我没事
These shoes are great! Where do you get these ideas?
这些鞋太棒了！你怎么想到的？
I'm calling it a "brain."
我管它叫脑子
I'm pretty sure it's where ideas come from.
我确信主意就是从这里产生的
Dad, I don't have a brain.
爸爸 我没有脑子
We've gotten along just fine without brains until now.
没脑子我们不也好好活到了现在
Cavemen don't need brains. We have these.
洞穴人不需要脑子 我们有这个
That's what I'm talking about! Ideas are for weaklings.
我们要的是这个 弱者才需要想点子！
Now, let's get to that mountain!
我们去那座山吧
Wow! I love those!
太好看了
Good fish. Don't eat my feet.
好鱼鱼 别吃我的脚
So, how did the tiger fly?
老虎是怎么飞起来的呢？
She jumped on the sun...
她跳上了太阳
and rode it to Tomorrow.
骑着它飞到了明天
No, no, no.
不 不 不！
Hi, Dad!
嗨 爸爸！
Bye, Dad!
拜拜 爸爸
You've seen rain before, right?
你们应该见过下雨吧？
We don't get out much.
我们不经常外出
Eep, looks dangerous.
小伊 看起来很危险
Dad, you say that about everything.
爸爸 你看什么都很危险
Careful.
小心啊
Really? Okay.
是吗？那好
No, no, no. Not cool!
不 不 不 不行啊！
So, the bear says, "Your cave? I've been dumping my bones here since last week."
- 那熊说：你的洞？我上星期就在这儿放骨头了,上星期!
That's a funny story!
真是个有意思的故事！
It's not a story. It's a joke.
这不是故事 是笑话
What's a "joke"?
什么是笑话？
Just making something up to make you laugh.
就是编点东西使你发笑
- One for you. - Thanks.
- 给你  - 谢谢
One for you. And this one's for you.
给你一个 这个给你…
Okay.
行了
Okay! That's enough!
行了 够了
I don't see why the kids need their own shells.
大家为什么需要这些贝壳？
So if anyone gets in trouble, we can call the others.
如果有人碰上了麻烦 可以向别人求救
Wait, you're saying we should split up?
等等 你说我们要分开？
We can try more paths at once.
这样我们可以一次试更多的路
It's the fastest way through.
这是最快的方法了
Croods stick together. Your way isn't safe.
克鲁家从不分开 你的方法不安全
They can handle it.
他们没事儿的
We can do it, Dad.
我们能行的 爸爸
No, no, no.
不 不 不
It's my job to keep you safe.
我是负责你们安全的
I'm still in charge and we are not splitting up.
我说了算 我们不会分开的
Except for you two.
你俩得分开
And that's final.
就这么定了
Hello?
喂？
Is everyone all right?
大家都好吗？
We're okay, Grug.
我们都好 古勒格！
Dad? I'm freaking out a little bit.
爸爸？我有点害怕
Just tell me what to do. What do I do? What do I do right now?
告诉我该怎么做 我该咋办啊？
Stay where you are. I'll find you.
留在原地别动！我去找你
No. Too slow.
不！那样太慢了
Everybody, keep moving forward and we'll get out.
大家都往前走 我们会出去的
Dad?
爸爸？
Yeah.
哎
Okay.
好吧
Remember, never not be afraid.
记住 不要不害怕
You can do this!
你能行的！
It's going to be okay, it's going to be okay.
没事儿的
I'm going to pass out.
我要昏过去了
Sandy. Sandy!
小沙！小沙！
Give me another one.
再给我一个
You dropped these.
你扔的吧
Come with me.
跟我走吧
Here, boy! Catch!
嘿 小子 接住！
Gran?
外婆？
Mom?
妈妈？
Wow.
哇
Grug?
古勒格呢？
I'll go get him.
我去找他
Good boy! Who's a good boy?
好孩子 谁是好孩子？
You are! Yes, you are! Look at you!
你是 没错 就是你 看看你
You need a name. You want a name?
你要名字吗？
I'm going to call you Douglas.
我叫你道格拉斯
Can you do tricks? Roll over.
你会演节目吗？滚一圈
Come on, Douglas, roll over.
来吧 道格拉斯 滚一圈
Good boy, Douglas!
好样的 道格拉斯！
I was in love once.
我爱上过一个人
He was a hunter. I was a gatherer.
他是猎人 我是采集食物的
It was quite a scandal.
当时闹得满城风雨呢
We fed each other berries, we danced.
我们彼此喂果子吃 一起跳舞
Then my father smashed him with a rock and traded me to your grandfather.
后来我爸爸用石头砸死了他 把我卖给了你们的外公
Croods!
克鲁家的
Get down here.
都下来！
Grug, they're okay. Guy is with them.
古勒格 他们挺好的 和盖在一起
Guy is with them. Okay.
和盖在一起 好
Thank you.
谢谢
Thank you for bringing me that interesting Guy update.
谢谢你告诉我那个盖的最新情况
Okay. I'm going to go up...
好了 我要上去了
and why don't you join us when you stop being a big drag!
等你不烦人了就上来和我们一起吧
Sleep pile?
要叠睡吗？
How about a story?
要听故事吗？
Anyone?
有人要吗？
And then Torg said, "Know it? I drew it."
托克说：知道 是我画的
That makes no sense.
没道理
I know it was hard for you to bring us along...
我知道你一路带着我们很不容易
but they had the best day of their lives.
但这几天是他们过得最开心的日子了
Thank you for that.
谢谢你
I want to show you something.
给你们看样东西
More suns in the sky than you can count.
天上有数不清的太阳
Every sun that crosses our sky comes to rest up there.
每颗穿过我们天空的太阳都在那里休息
Tomorrow.
明天
That's where we'll be safe.
我们在那里会很安全
I'm going with Guy.
我要和盖一起去
No. Not my little girl.
不 不要带走我女儿
Come with us.
和我们一起来吧
I can't go without Grug.
我不能丢下古勒格
That makes one of us. Count me in.
我不在乎 算我一个
Really, Mom? Now?
真的吗？妈妈？
Grug has no idea how to protect us.
古勒格不知道怎么保护我们
In fact, he has no ideas at all!
其实他没有任何点子
No, that's not true. What about that one time when he...
不 不对 有一次他…呃…
Face it.
承认吧
If he actually had an idea of his own...
如果他真能想出什么点子
I'd have a heart attack and die!
我会震惊得心脏病发而死的！
Grug?
古勒格？
- Dad! - Dad!
- 爸爸？  - 爸爸？
He's a big guy. How could he just disappear like that?
这么大个人哪能消失了呢？
Hey, wait! Let's ask that ugly lady if she's seen Dad.
等等 问问那个丑女人是否见到了爸爸
Haven't seen him.
我没见到他
What are you doing?
你在干什么？
I was up all night, because all these ideas just kept coming to me.
我昨晚彻夜未眠 简直是灵感如泉涌
Is that a snake?
那是蛇吗？
Belt, new and improved.
是皮带！最新改良款！
It's even self-tightening!
带自动收紧功能
What is that on your head?
你头上戴的是什么？
It's called desperation.
是绝望
I call it a "rug." Rhymes with "Grug."
我叫它“发壳” 跟“古勒格”押韵
And this one, I call it a "ride."
这个是…我叫它“轱辘球”
Rhymes with "Grug."
和“古勒格”押韵
That doesn't rhyme...
一点也不押韵…
It's going to get us places faster than shoes.
它比鞋要快
Yeah! Try to keep up!
耶！要跟上哦！
I wish I had a ride.
我也要轱辘球
And painting is a thing of the past.
画画已经过时了
I call this a "snapshot."
我管它叫“快拍”
Let's do it again. I think I blinked.
再来一次 我眨眼了
I call them "shades."
我叫这个“眼罩”
The sun doesn't hurt my eyes anymore.
阳光伤不到我的眼睛了
Where do you get these great ideas?
你从哪想出这些点子的？
Since I don't have a brain...
因为没有脑子
they're coming from my stomach, down deep below...
它们是从我胃里反出来
and then up again into my mind.
进入脑壳的
Grug, we have to keep moving.
古勒格 我们得赶路啊
See, I got ideas. I got thoughts.
看 我有点子 我有想法
Like this. I call it a "mobile home."
这个 我叫它“移动的家”
Isn't that something?
牛吧？
And I'm calling this one a "lifterator."
这个是“抬升器”
Mom?
妈妈？
I know. It's bad.
我知道 要悲剧了
I almost feel sorry for him.
我都快看不下去了
No, I don't.
不 我还看得下去
What are you trying to do, Grug?
你这是想干什么啊 古勒格？
See, I thought if I could have ideas...
我想如果我能像盖一样
Iike Guy...
有很多点子
maybe Eep would listen to me.
也许小伊就会听我的
And maybe she wouldn't want to go with Guy.
也许她就不会想跟盖走了
Grug.
古勒格
Is that what this is all about?
就因为这点事儿？
And I also thought it would kill your mother.
我还希望这样能弄死你妈
So win- win.
所以…算是双赢吧
We're here!
我们到了！
Cave!
山洞！
Everyone inside.
大家都进去！
Hurry up. Let's go.
快！快！快进去啊！
Let's go. Go!
快进去啊！
No!
不！
No more caves, Grug.
不要再住山洞了 古勒格
What?
什么？
We're going to jump on the sun and ride it to Tomorrow with Guy!
我们要跳上太阳骑着它和盖一起去明天
Wait. So you're all going to do this?
等等 你们都要走吗？
Thunk?
桑克？
Sorry, Dad.
对不起 爸爸
You have to stop worrying for all of us.
你不要再为我们担心了
It's my job to worry! It's my job to follow the rules!
这是我的责任 我要遵循规定
The rules don't work out here!
在这里规则不管用！
They kept us alive!
规则使我们活下来！
That wasn't living! That was just not dying.
那不是活着 只是…没死而已
There's a difference.
两者是有区别的
Ugga, everyone, you have to listen to me.
阿加 大伙 你们得听我的！
We would be dead if we listened to you!
要是听你的我们早死了！
We have to follow Guy now.
我们现在听盖的
Guy.
盖？
Guy? Run.
盖 快跑！
This is pointless!
别这样！
We're running out of time. Everything is collapsing.
我们时间不多了 世界在崩塌
You're being irrational and counterproductive!
你这是不理性 是在弄巧成拙
Big words anger me!
那些文绉绉的词儿激怒我了!
Keep talking.
继续说啊!
Countermeasures!
启动防御装置!
You remember how you were this morning? You changed.
记得今早的你吗？你变了
Idea man. Modern man.
成了有想法的人 现代人
I am a caveman!
我是洞穴人！
No, no, no, wait!
不 不 不要啊！
No!
不！
What is this stuff that saves you from my punches?
这不让我揍你的东西是什么？
Tar.
柏油
No. I have to get back to them.
不！我得回去找他们！
Stop struggling.
别乱动！
No!
不！
Grug, stop!
快停下 古勒格！
No one gets out of this.
没人能出去的
Believe me...
相信我
I know.
我知道的
Your...
你的…？
Family. Yeah.
家人 没错
Sorry.
对不起
I was little when it happened.
当时我还很小
Last thing my parents told me was...
我父母对我说的最后一件事是
"Don't hide.
不要躲藏
"Live.
活下去
"Follow the sun.
追随太阳
"You'll make it to Tomorrow."
你就能到达明天
You followed the light.
你追随光明
My daughter is a lot like you.
我女儿很像你
No.
不
She's like you.
她像你
She loves you, but always forgets to say it.
她很爱你 只是忘了对你说
Just like you forget to tell her.
就像你忘了对她说一样
I guess I was just busy keeping them all alive.
我想我只是忙着让他们活下去
It's okay. That's what dads do.
这没错 做爸爸的都是这样
That's right.
没错
But we can't do that from here.
我们困在这里可成不了事
We need one of your ideas.
你得想个主意出来
Come on. You can do it.
来吧 你能行的
Belt! Emergency Idea Generator, activate!
皮带猴 紧急点子制造机 启动！
I've got it.
有了
Wow.
哇
Yeah, I know. But he's doing the best with what he has.
我知道 但是他能做成这样已经不错了
Let's go.
来吧
There he is.
他在那儿
Belt, I want romance, drama, sincerity.
皮带猴 来点浪漫的 戏剧的 真诚的
Move me.
让我动起来
Okay, he sees us.
好了 他看见我们了！
That's our cue. Now, work it!
信号来了 快弄！
He's not coming over.
他没过来
I don't think our puppet looks scared enough.
我想是我们的木偶显得不够害怕
Scared? I'll show you scared.
害怕？这我擅长！
Hand me those acting sticks!
把棍子都给我！
Hold on!
抓住！
Yes! You did it.
噢耶！你成功了！
- Grug! - Dad!
- 古勒格！  - 爸爸！
Hey! We're okay!
嘿！我们没事儿！
Yeah.
是啊
We're okay.
我们没事儿
Grug, your call.
古勒格 你发话
Take us to Tomorrow.
带我们去明天吧
Hurry!
快点！
Come on! We're going to make it!
来吧！我们可以的！
You were right.
没错！
There it is! The sun!
就在那儿！太阳！
We can do it! We can ride it to Tomorrow!
我们能行的！我们能骑着它去明天！
Run!
快跑！
I don't understand.
这是…这是为什么
The sun was right here. It was right here.
太阳就在这儿 就在这儿！
We have to go back to the cave.
我们得回洞里了！
Hurry, hurry, hurry.
快 快 快
Stay together. Let's keep moving. Move, move, move.
呆在一起！快走 走啊…走！
Everybody, hold my hand.
都拉住我的手！
Thunk, let's go. Go, go, go. Let's stay together.
桑克 快走！快 呆在一起！
Grug. What's wrong with you?
古勒格 你怎么了？
Grug, we'll die if we stay here!
古勒格 快走 不然会死的！
Grug, listen to me.
古勒格 听我的
We've got to get back to that cave.
我们得回山洞里去
No more dark.
不再有黑暗
No more hiding.
不再去躲藏
No more caves.
不再住山洞了
What's the point of all this?
这些都有什么意义呢？
To follow the light.
要追随光明去
I can't change.
我改变不了
I don't have ideas.
我想不出主意
But I have my strength.
但是我有力气
And right now...
此刻
that's all you need.
这正是你们所需要的
No, we don't know what's over there. Maybe nothing!
不！我们不知道那边有什么！可能什么都没有
It's too risky!
这太冒险了
It's a chance.
这是个机会
I'll take that chance.
我来试试吧
I've wanted to throw you away ever since I met you.
自从我第一见到你 我就想把你扔出去
That's a joke, right?
你在开玩笑 是不？
What's a "joke"?
什么是开玩笑？
He made it!
他成功了！
He made it.
他成功了
Okay, Thunk. Your turn.
好了 桑克 该你了
You're not coming, are you?
你不一起过来吗？
When you make it, so will I.
你过去了我就去
No!
不！
You did good.
你做得很好
Dadda!
爸爸
Gran...
外婆…
No mush. Just throw me.
别肉麻了 快扔吧
Wait.
等等！
You surprised me today...
你今天让我刮目相看
Iunkhead.
呆瓜
Still alive!
我还活着！
Time to go.
该走了
No.
不！
I have too much to say to you.
我有太多想说的话
I need to fix everything, and I don't have time.
我需弥补一切 但来不及了
I can fix it.
我能弥补
This works good.
这感觉真好
What do you call it?
你管它叫什么？
I was thinking of calling it a "hug."
我想叫它“拥合”
Because it rhymes with "Grug."
因为和“古勒格”押韵
But you can change it if you want.
你要不喜欢可以改
No. I like "hug."
不 我喜欢“拥合”
I love you.
我爱你
I...
我…
Dad...
爸爸
I'm scared.
我害怕
Never be afraid.
不要害怕
There!
那儿！
I see him!
我看见他了
Hey!
嘿！
Hey, I did it!
我成功了
Back! Stay back!
别过来！
Stay back!
They're in trouble.
他们危险了
Hang on, I'm coming!
坚持住！我来了！
How do I get across?
我该怎么过去呢？
I have to think. What would Guy do?
我得想想 盖会怎么做？
What would Guy do, what would Guy do?
盖会怎么做？盖会怎么做？
What would I do?
我会怎么做？
Hold this.
拿着
I have...
我想到了…
an idea!
一个好主意！
Run!
快跑！
Yes!
太好了
Douglas?
道格拉斯！
Hey, I know that guy.
我认识他！
Hold on!
坚持住！
It's not safe here.
这里不安全
I'll tell her.
我去告诉她
I never got to tell him.
我都没来得及告诉他
Eep, if your dad were here, he would tell you to...
小伊 如果你爸爸在这儿的话 他会和你说…
Get out of the way!
闪开！
Wow. You sound just like him.
哇 你学得好像啊
Get out of the way!
闪开！
Dadda!
爸爸！
He did it!
他成功了！
He's riding the sun.
他骑着太阳
But, not very well.
但骑得不太好
Everybody out of the way!
大家闪开！
- Dad! - Grug!
- 爸爸  - 古勒格！
Where's the danger? Who blew their shell?
危险在哪儿？谁吹的号角？
I love you, too!
我也爱你！
One, two, three, four...
一 二 三 四
five...
五
six...
六
and seven.
七
And a half.
七个半
And eight.
还有八
Nine.
九
Douglas! Dad, you saved him!
道格拉斯！爸爸 你救了他！
A boy has to have a pet.
男孩应该有个宠物
Turns out I'm a cat person.
没想到我和猫处得不错
No.
不行！
You really need to see this.
你们快来看
We should go there.
我们应该去那里
Yes! Coming through!
耶！我来啦！
Wait!
等等
This is me. My name is Eep.
这就是我 小伊
And this is my family, the Croods.
这是我的家人 克鲁家族
If you weren't clued in by the suntans and pets...
你应该能从晒黑的皮肤和宠物
we're not exactly cavemen anymore.
判断出我们不再是穴居人了
Let's do it again. I think I blinked.
再来一次 我眨眼了
Our world is still plenty harsh and hostile...
我们的世界依旧充满了危险与困难
but now we know the Croods will make it.
但现在我们知道克鲁家族能应付得了
Because we changed the rules...
因为我们改变了规矩
the ones that kept us in the dark.
不再遵循把我们囚在黑暗里的规定
And because of my dad, who taught us that anyone can change.
也因为我爸爸 他教会了我们人皆可变
Release the baby!
放孩子！
Sort of.
算是吧
So, from now on,we'll stay out here...
所以 从现在开始 我们住在这里
where we can follow the light.
这个能追随光明的地方